Recording is in progress,
and
I will call this regular meeting of the Andover
Inland Butlands and Water Courses Commission to order at 07:00
on Tuesday, 02/07/2022.
I see on screen
the
Commissioners
Larson
and Monroe are present, as well as myself,
so I guess that leaves only Ed Smith
absent.
Next item on the agenda would be changes in order to the agenda.
I don't have any. Does anybody else have any to suggest in terms of
additions or changes
in order to the agenda?
Seeing none,
we'll move to item number four, approval of minutes.
First of all, the minutes for
01/11/2022,
our regular meeting.
Does anyone have
comments or
changes,
corrections,
I should say,
to those minutes.
Had one
item that I noted.
Item number three on
the minutes,
which was changes in order of the agenda,
the motion was carried by unanimous
consent
rather than anonymous.
We
were there. We were speaking.
Other than that, I didn't notice anything. Did anyone else
catch anything?
If not, I'll move approval. I'm sorry. Approve those minutes.
Ask for a second.
I'll second.
>> Okay, second by
Commissioner Monroe,
and those in favor can signify
by raising their hands to signify aye.
Okay,
the bonus unanimous.
Next,
minutes from our sidewalk
and special meeting,
that occurred
on January
22.
I have no comments.
>> Okay.
Okay,
so if we don't have any suggestions or corrections or changes,
again, I'll move that we accept those or approve those minutes
and ask for the second. I'll second.
Okay, so motion and second.
All in favor, again, raise your hand to say aye. Okay,
and the motion is carries unanimously.
That brings us to the section on public comment.
And I don't believe we have any,
so we will move to old business,
item number six.
The first item of old business is the
application
number
for
work to be done at Number 3 Lakeside Drive.
I see the applicant,
Gary McCullough, is on the call,
And I note that since our last consideration
of this, of course, we've had the sidewalk
at that location.
And
we also
received
one
bit of information
in the form of an
approval
by the Androval Management Association
for the
lake wall rebuild
and dock removal
portion of that project,
those affecting the lake bed.
And we also received some information that
Agent Wagner dug out of the files
regarding the original
permit back in 1993
for the construction of the sand beach
that was at issue in the original
application.
Now,
as I understand it, there's been some discussion between Agent Wagner and the applicant
regarding this project
and trying to get it to
the point where we can go ahead and work on it.
So,
I guess I'll ask first if the applicant has any
immediate comments to make on that application.
>> Well,
I guess thanks to for Alma for the approval
on the,
you know, on the on the rock wall side of things.
And
looking forward to your guys'
feedback
on what
Joe and I have put together regarding
the next steps for the the
the,
you know, the sand beach.
>> Okay.
I wanted to ask you a question. Will the
wall restoration
rebuild
necessitate working on the lake bed?
I know you have permission from Alma to do it, but there is the question of high water
and getting the, you know, in others, is it going to be necessary for this work to be done before the lake is razed?
>> I would say we'd want to get that work done before the lake is raised, yes. Okay,
>> the sand beach part, because it's going to be perched and away
from the
lake bed,
wouldn't be as critical, but I thought that I wanted to clarify that aspect,
okay, because it obviously has to do with the timing of issuing the permit as well.
>> I Right. Had something. This is a agent Wagner. I
just wanted to make you aware, chairman. I'm not sure if you notice
because it came in a really late
addition I sent to
all the commission members was a revised project
plan
for this application.
So it only sent maybe like a half hour ago.
Didn't know the right.
Yeah. Then a
couple of revised descriptions with the
with the new
perched beach construction, a diagram of the the riprap wall and stuff. So
I don't know if anyone had to take a chance to take a look at it. Like I said, it was really last minute. So
but you guys should have that on in your email.
I got it.
>> I've got that as well, agent Wagner, but I have to say how disheartening it is
to log into my computer to attend a meeting that I spent a lot of time preparing for. Right. And once again, the second meeting in a row, find
that there is a updated
plan, if you will, that I've had, I have not had a chance to look at until we walk in the door for this meeting.
That I
find that very disrespectful
to the time I spend trying to prepare to have a good discussion
on an application.
>> I
would, tend to agree with that. The
fact is that,
you know, I don't think it's fair to commissioners to,
try to
comprehend the changes and updates in
real time
during the meeting.
And
so, I would
appreciate it. I think it would be good in any event if we could,
if Agent Wagner could walk us through
the changes that are intended,
I
am going to propose
that we
defer
a vote on this,
and that, you know, we may have to ask for an extension on the
with respect to the deadline for action
on this application.
But in any event, as I say, a good summary
of the
changes
in the plan
would be useful at this time.
>> Yeah. I'd like to, yeah,
know, move on forward as best we can.
I'll
apologize up front.
We kind of were
waiting for the approval from Alma to occur
because we knew we couldn't go any do anything until we had that.
But we got that over the weekend.
You know, they did the best they could to pull that together.
And then,
you know, we
took and
looked through all the information at hand and
think we put together a pretty good proposal here.
And things we've, I think we've covered a lot of concern areas.
My goal,
and again, I apologize and had no intent to be disrespectful
or try to pull a fast one or anything like that.
So if we could move forward in good faith here and, you know,
if Joe could
walk us through this
and
let you guys digest it and we can come back at the next meeting for more discussion or whatever we have to do.
Know, I'll just leave it at that. But this was not intended to be a disrespectful
event.
Thank
you for that.
Aaron Joe, do you think
>> not sure that coming back to the next meeting is even an option because once we approve it, you've got a two week waiting period
before
the work can start.
And that gets us to
the time where
we're planning to raise the water level in the lake.
And so I would like to start the discussion tonight
by addressing the actions we're going to take
to remediate
the violation
that we have in existence and has
existed since
last October
where
there's a significant amount of new sand added to the lake bed that we need to make sure we get out of there before we start raising the water level in the lake. Right.
>> So as soon as as soon as it
unfreezes,
I mean, I try to it's it's like hard as a rock.
But I've got resources
to to to pull that out as soon as it's we're we're able to do that. So that will absolutely happen. That's the first priority.
>> That is not listed as the first step in your plan.
>> I know we had talked about that
and had permission or I
don't even know if it was permission. It was
I was told to do that, and I said, yes, I would do that.
So we can add that as the first step, but that that has been a a given from,
you know,
from the beginning is once I heard this was not a good thing, I stopped everything
and was told to really cease and desist and wait for the process to be told what to do.
>> Okay, so let's take it as read that removal of sand from the lake that will be the first action
and will occur
as soon as possible.
>> I'm
still concerned,
again, this
is probably a question that nobody wants asked,
But how are we going to get the sand out of the lake bed?
>> I think it'd be worth going through that, what resources you have available and how you plan on doing it. Yeah, well, it's going to be, we're going to take shovels and put them in wheelbarrows. I got a
>> lawn tractor. We're gonna pull wheelbarrows up and
do that. I mean, we're not gonna bring in any heavy equipment in.
We're gonna go down to the level of
where, you know, where it was.
>> That's gonna take quite a few people. You got about 10 yards of sand there, right? About 10. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. And
>> again, I'll just reiterate,
you know, the water level goes up starting the third weekend, roughly third weekend in March.
Yeah. That's when we close the valve. It takes about a week or two to get up to summer level.
Yep.
>> It'll be later. On the initial application,
it said the amount of sand was 10 to 15 yards.
Do we know exactly how much sand was delivered?
>> Well, it was in the the lake bed. So there's there's sand that was put above the
the the the lake
in the existing beach.
And then there was some sand put down below.
So,
you know, it's
between the two, it's 15, but there's probably and these are all estimate. Mean, I I I
they're estimates.
So it's, you know, saying it's probably,
you know,
I don't I you know, it's probably 10
I think about it, it's probably more on the beach side.
On the land side, it's probably more like
eight or nine there, and it's probably,
you know, six or seven
down below. But it's, you know, it's the total.
>> It was just my perception from the sidewalk that the majority of the sand was in the beach. But the your yard was covered with snow, so it made it a little bit hard to tell.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it is hard to tell. But, yeah, I mean, that existing beach kind of goes back further than the than the the you know,
how as far out than it goes into the water. It's more,
you know, more on the land than into the water.
But
>> I said 10 because, you know, it was just
an estimate. So there may be a little bit more there. Know, it was gonna be spread out.
>> Well, did you, yeah, did you order it by the truckload or did you order, you know, normally I go get my mulch and I buy it, you know, by the yard so I know exactly how many yards
I've got. But that's probably a bigger
amount than what I would be used to for mulch.
>> Yeah, right.
Yeah, so it was,
it was 15,
but some of it's on the land and some of it's in the water.
So to say exactly how much, I mean, we could just say $50.50
or $60.40.
I
don't wanna misread you know, I I I don't know
for sure.
Okay. I understand.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
>> So with the understanding that that all the sand is going to be removed
from below the high water mark
and that
the remaining sand,
some of it you intend to redistribute
above the
200 foot setback line, and
some of it will go into the proposed
sandbox
or
perched beach, if you will,
then
we have then,
again, an understanding that, there won't be any sand left beyond,
or none of the newly deposited sand will remain
either
on the so called beach
or
below the high water mark. Eventually, it's all going to get relocated.
That's
the intent, yes. Then
>> Joe, could you bring up on or
Davy and Joe, can you bring up that plan? I don't have, for some reason, my
male client is refusing to find new male for me, so I haven't even had a chance to look at the
revised
and the most recent update.
So, in order to be on the same page, I'd like to be able to see the page.
>> Joe, I can share it if you'd like, or you can. It might be easier if you do, Joe, so you can walk through it, but I can share it as well. Oh, yeah, if you want to share it, that'd be good. Okay. Probably
More experienced.
Okay.
>> This is the
first page is the proposed
project plan
that's updated
But the existing stone lake walls
to the north and south end are going to be
reconstructed
as riprap walls
>> and they'll slope away from the lake and they'll be constructed. We're not looking at a picture, Joe. We're looking at the project description.
>> Yeah, know. I'm also looking at the script first. We're just going through the whole thing.
So, yeah,
riprap top layer, then a layer of fabric underneath the riprap, and they'll be crushed on for drainage underneath.
And no machinery will be used on the lake bed.
And then the existing dock will be removed,
which will need hand tools to remove the two pilings in the lake bed.
And then
the existing
sand beach will be moved behind
the 25
foot long by three foot high riprap wall.
And then this will create the perched beach and the sand will be contained by four by four posts buried in the ground.
So the area will be dug out as necessary to provide for approximately
10 inches of finished sand depth.
The four by four posts will be stacked as necessary to contain sand and account for elevation changes
along the edges of the beach and then the top of the post will will be elevated above the surface of the lawn. So that will prevent the sand, you know, one prevent the sand from
leaving the area and then it'll prevent
water that's coming downhill
during a rain event from washing any of the sand out.
And then that that whole area will be lined with the geotextile
fabric, and then it'll be brought up and attached near the top of the 4x4 posts to prevent the sand from leaching out of anything.
And then that area where the sink sand beach is will be will be restored to a lawn area.
So if you could move down to the
to the next page,
this is like an updated site plan shows the
four by four perched beach area behind the stonewall.
And then it'll shows the filter fabric behind the riprap wall.
And then if you go on to the next page,
that's the detail,
the riprap with the fabric underneath it, and then the crushed stone underneath that,
and then the
detail for the
the the beach.
>> Why did we shift from a rebuild of the stone wall to a riprap wall?
The Gary, do you have
Well,
>> when
I was looking at the
recommendations,
it it said to that that was preferred
preferred method is a roof rack wall.
That was preferred material.
>> I would venture
to say based on the 1993
photographs
that,
Agent Wagner found in the files
that it
was
hardly a wall
to begin with,
and
that the proposed
RIPRAP barrier,
if you will,
would be a distinct, well, certainly an improvement over the existing conditions.
And
it wasn't so much
a matter of
rebuilding a wall as creating one.
And I was, by the way, interested to note that in the top of the in the upper of the three photographs,
if you recall those
photos that again
from the 1993
application,
it looks like in the background
there's basically a sandbox
with
very light construction
equipment,
The kind of thing my grandson might like to play with.
>> Well, the thing I liked about the three foot high.
Stonewall.
Was it created?
At least to my mind, a significant buffer
between the sand and the lake
where the riffrapped
wall
continues a slope down into the lake.
Yeah.
>> And I did not see in the document where
it talked about riprap was preferred,
did say
natural stone,
riprap, or a
stone wall.
>> Well, I I think we were also
somewhere
we've
said that we're gonna have that stone wall
tilting back towards the, you
know, away from from bottom to top, away from the water,
angled back a bit.
>> But it would not, I mean, riprap wall won't, won't extend above the lawn or above the sand. It'll, it'll be at that level
or at the top of the riprap wall.
>> The sand would be
not all the way to the top of that wall.
Okay.
That's the intent.
>> I think the, the elevation shows,
the
four by four posts,
basically,
that will be retaining
the sand,
above the level,
it's above grade of the lawn
in cross section.
And you have the fabric beneath it.
>> Right. And also is,
I'm not sure that that slope
indicated
in the cross sectional drawing
with riprap top there, I'm not sure that the lawn,
based on the photographs and recollection
from our sidewalk,
that there is actually a slope to the lawn at that point.
It's pretty flat in that area.
It flattens out.
>> So, so
you are not going to rebuild the stonewall, you're going to replace it with a riprap wall or are you still planning on rebuilding it in some areas?
>> Well, I would say that
if there's some some foundation,
you know, there's a
footprint there of a wall, right? And some of it is stone. I think if there's some of that that can be used and then
build above that, you know, on top of whatever we can salvage.
So I guess that might be a hybrid sort of approach where it's not a rip and replace for sure. It's I think we're gonna try and
leverage whatever
material is there and then build up on it.
Okay.
>> Because in the permit that we approved, I mean, was basically to rebuild the stone wall that had been there.
>> Well,
I mean,
and then
it's because
I'm
not as the smartest guy in the world. I thought that we could,
you know, use this material
if we want to use all stone.
I'm I'm not married to any
type of materials. If you guys are telling me you want roof rack, you want stone, I'll I'll
go with the stone.
And then.
>> Yeah, I mean, I think. Riffrapp is stone. It's just a question of whether it's range.
And as I say, when look at
the photograph
of the
wall as it existed in 1993,
it's not really a wall. There's some stone there,
and it's pretty rough,
and
it's
maybe already deteriorating.
But,
you know, in
the sense of trying to rebuild to that condition,
I don't think that would be a desirable objective,
either aesthetically or
functionally.
And so, although as
the applicant has pointed out,
using
the existing material,
you know, what's still there,
would certainly be
beneficial
and desirable.
There's going to have to be more in order to make a sufficient retaining
wall out of this, or
either way,
material is going to have to be brought in.
And the question is, you know, is it preferable to have
a laid
structured wall,
or will the riprap
have the same
function
and
do the job adequately?
>> I haven't seen the photograph from 1993,
so I don't know what it looked like back then. I assume it's not much different than it looks now.
>> Well,
actually, maybe Abby, could you
bring that up? It's the the document is labeled photos.
Of Project Lakeside Drive 1993
Photos of Project.
It's in the application
materials,
I believe.
>> I see pictures of proposed projects
and pictures from agent visit. That's 2022.
Oh, okay. So those were just circulated by email?
>> I think so. Yeah, okay.
I caution you to this agent Wagner. I just caution you to, you know, not
consider.
20, you know 20 year old pictures. Well, 23
year old pictures really
as like a pre existing condition. I mean, lot could have happened between then and.
Sure. And now so yeah,
>> right, but we don't have any app. We don't have any application or any permit
for, you know, there would have been a per there should have been a permit if any further work was done on the wall
between then and now.
Yeah, hopefully.
It didn't always happen, but
>> My expectation coming to the meeting tonight was there was going to be a three foot high retaining wall
that
in spite of the lack of.
A lot of other stones there
was going to be, you'll have extra stone brought in to build a nicely finished wall,
just like we see at all the other places that have rebuilt the wall.
>> Riprap can be good in a way though, because the
angle it dissipates wave energy a little better than than
your typical
90 degree.
You know, finished more finished wall which can
so it can
be a preferred method.
The gently
sloping area kind of does
a little bit better job of recreating a natural shoreline.
Then
the abrupt
upright wall that you see.
>> Yeah, and we have riprap walls, the Dowling's put in a riprap wall
a couple of years ago in front of their place. Yep, I,
>> and I like the wall that they put in over there. It was just a question I'm trying to, I have tried very hard to convince myself that putting all this sand next to the beach is a good idea. Yeah. And, you know, with the wall that was there, I thought I had, I like the four by four post
perimeter
around it. I,
you know,
I thought that was
a good idea. I thought it was specified
in the,
you know, the New Hampshire document. It also talks about,
you know, swales around it too.
I don't know.
I convinced myself maybe a swale wasn't necessary if we had the four by four posts or the railroad ties
with the three foot high wall. Certainly
we could keep the sand out of the beach.
I was
in,
I think I have the pictures from '93
so that if I were to share the screen, could pull it up. The thing that impressed
me about those pictures
was the size of the sandpile
that we used to construct the beach.
And I have to ask myself, where's that sand now?
And the answer to that is it's all in the lake.
And I'm trying very hard because as that document
described,
vulnerable lakes are shallow lakes,
which ours is very shallow.
Climate change, if you will, is resulting in the
lake heating up, and so we're having more problems
with that. And
as a property owner on the lake, you know, I feel compelled to try and
make sure we're doing what we can to protect the lake.
But anyhow,
I came here
tonight hoping to have a great friendly conversation
and I just
got derailed when I saw here's a new plan and hadn't had a chance to look at it.
But I'm ready to, I'll listen now.
>> Yeah, so this is Gary.
Know, when I'm thinking of this,
the
wall, the 25 foot wall, then there's this open spot where the beach was. There. Back
in '93 and all this time, there was a beach there was no retaining wall there. There was nothing there.
And then on the corner
on the corner of the property where the seven seven foot wall, seven and a half foot wall, just a corner there,
that was, there was another wall there.
So that sand had nothing holding it back all this time. When I saw that and I took into consideration,
you know, all these things I'm learning and the concerns
and working with the information I have,
I really thought this, you know, retaining wall, a beach that seemed like a really nice kind of, not even a compromise, but a solution
to,
you know, how to do this.
And,
you know, I'm not a late guy. I'm not a well,
you know,
expert in all this. And I'm
working as we go here,
trying to, you know,
make
make the best
plan
and taking all these considerations and that's
I was hoping and I think we are having a good conversation.
So, I I think if we can continue along that is is are we on the right track here to build
a riffraff wall if riffraff is no good, but Joe thinks, you know, feels that it's good, maybe not as aesthetically pleasing, but it may be different other people have done it. I'm okay with it.
We contain that sand, we remove the sand that's there,
because it's
not doing anybody any good anymore.
And we do that.
The details,
this is I think that's where we're at now is
the detail part. Are we on the right track? You know,
just gotta ask that.
>> I can't
say that we're on the wrong track. It's just, you know, I went out and carefully considered
the track that
was
sprung on me at the last minute at the last meeting
and
was happy to address
that plan.
Not that RipRap's,
maybe it is better, I don't know.
All I could do was go out and study the plan that was presented.
>> Correct.
Could we scroll down to the final page of this new? I want to see what else we've got. Okay, the overview
with the, okay, the existing sand beach
and
the,
okay, the sand, the stone bank
and dock
existing conditions.
So
again,
okay, I'm not quite clear here what would be the setback
between
the
proposed riprap wall
and
the
sandbox or the perched beach?
Setback?
Yeah, I mean, there's a Would there be
>> so there there'd be the
geo
the fabric,
and then there's gonna be some
gravel.
So I, you know, I don't know. I
couldn't say it's a
foot or so maybe. I don't know.
>> Okay. But some separation,
physical separation between
the riprap and
the,
well, we'll call it the lower
retaining
post
or railroad tie, the 4x4.
So, you know, what I'm looking at is, again, do we have adequate measures in place here to prevent sand
from eroding
from
the Perch Beach
into the lake? I mean, it seems to me that that's really an essential question
about this design.
We want to get, you
know, the
Andover Lake Management Association,
which owns the lake says or owns the lake bed, says no
sand,
okay? We don't want sand. The
wetlands regulations
say we should be avoiding erosion
of material into a water course.
So, we're mutually agreed that we don't want sand
moving into the lake, right?
And the question is, do we have adequate measures in place to achieve
that?
Now,
Agent Wagner, you were saying that
based on your understanding of the,
for example, the information we have from New Hampshire and so forth, that a riprap wall,
sloped riprap wall, would be equally as effective as a vertical,
retaining wall
in
making a transition between
the
lake
and that the design would prevent erosion.
Correct?
Yes.
>> Seems to me that that would be a an improvement on the existing condition.
I got to look at the plan as a whole and I see I mean that you can tell looking at the little picture that
it's obviously filled that was brought in to build the lawn. That's kind of what the the edge of the wall looks like. You know, this boulders that were pushed out when they were grading and then they put the topsoil over it.
So I mean, putting the riprap there wouldn't
wouldn't be a huge change to the existing condition, but it would. It would prevent some erosion.
Of the lawn into the lake, which is good, and also by relocating
the beach.
And restoring that to a more natural shoreline.
I think I mean overall the plan seems like it's it's a net positive.
For the for the short and eliminate the.
You know 999%
of the erosion risk of the existing conditions.
Which you know, even if even if the applicant removes.
The sand that he put there, there's there's still some sand there
from before. So so by, you know, kind of letting that grow up into a grass grassy area
on more natural shoreline.
I think
I don't know, I think it's just a net positive.
>> By the way,
Jed, you were asking about the quantity of sand.
By my top of the head reckoning,
the original project must have required about 12 yards
of sand
to get it to the dimensions that they specify
in the permit.
Okay.
>> And you're right. Of that, probably 10 is
now further out from the shore.
Okay,
so
the question is, how do we want to proceed? We've got, you know, really we have
three components to this. We have,
first of all, is the
cease and correct, that is getting the sand out
from its present location. We're sure that's going to happen
as soon as possible.
Second would be the
reconstruction.
Of course, the third part is the removal
of the dock. That was approved by Elm, and
I
don't know that there are any issues with that. That's all handwork, and any application
to replace that dock would be a subsequent
issue, right? There's no consideration
now, as I understand it, to replacing that dock.
>> That's correct.
That's right. Right. Okay. I just wanna get rid of it. It's a eyesore and it's dangerous, and I may not ever put a dock in there or next year.
Maybe we'll we'll go down that path, but that's not in that's not in the plan. Just want to get rid of it.
>> So are there further
questions
or
comments
on the application,
and I'd like to get some sense of how we should proceed
with the application at this point in time.
>> Yeah. Chair Elliott, I had a Yeah.
What you were, like, talking asking,
I don't know if that was really answered. The
the question of the splash over from the that
with the riprap type
wall,
you know,
in the distance between that riprap wall
in your your sandbox,
if you will.
There,
there maybe should be a little distance between the wall and the in the in the perch beach.
Because
to keep that splash
over splash
from,
you know, pulling that sand out of there, even if even if you got a four by four.
If there's enough water flying over the
over the wall,
it's it's going to wash that sand out of there.
Unless you're far enough away where the splash isn't landing in the
in the
beach perched beach.
There should be a difference between those two
items that you're planning to put in.
>> I Yeah.
I mean, if you guys want it, yeah. My
only,
I can't say because
I
was never here during the season.
And
the water down there is pretty shallow.
I don't know that there's,
a lot of wave action that comes flashing over. I could be totally wrong.
But if from a design perspective,
the consensus is that we need
some material.
I don't know
what we would do in between
there. We might have to add material
in between, right? We've got that fabric there
up against the wall to keep
stuff going out, but you're worried about the splash and then the splash causing
the seal to jump out kind of thing?
>> It would puddle eventually. I mean, there's a lot.
Down that part of the lake, I'm not sure if you get the kind of waves that
you see at some of the other sections. I'm not sure. It gets pretty
wavy.
Mean there's.
>> Well,
instance, on one of the big storms last summer,
the water in the lake
was,
I saw it 14
inches above
the
spillway level that it just filled up so much
by coming in there and that you know that raised the high.
Water level.
Around the perimeter of the lake
significantly.
>> Yeah, I think the max we got to was 18 inches actually.
Okay,
that's a
big increase.
>> Yeah.
Could you
back
to page number two
of the
document
on screen?
Okay, yeah.
In
that diagram,
it does appear
that the sandbox is pretty much buttered at
the wall.
Hold on a second. I'm getting you that unstable
internet
message.
Appears to have cleared it up. Okay,
yeah,
the question here is, would a little bit of setback then
help in, again, prevent, you know, again, the main objective to prevent sand
From
eroding
into
the lake.
>> So so
I mean, so from a design perspective, would that just be like an open space there or what would we have the
two by fours there. But what
what would we put in between? What would the buffer then be? What would you suggest that be?
>> Possibly
third four by four on top or make it an
or something of that nature. I don't know if that would do it.
I I'm not I'm not familiar with the riprap wall. So that's,
I mean, is it good? Is that gonna
reduce the amount of the size of these waves? Or is it gonna
deflect the water in a
better than a rock wall or
it's sloped like that? I don't know. It almost seems like it would be easier for the water to go up up and over that.
>> Look, I was just this agent Wagner. I'm just looking at the
the map
of
Where 3 Lakeside Drive is on the lake, I mean it's kind of.
Step back in a in a cold.
A little bit, so I'm not sure.
It'd be hard to see.
Like the way the the White Lake Wall is facing and kind of faces towards the other side of the cove,
so there's really not going to be a whole lot of fetch in that area.
So I don't know. Could see how like like flood water might may affect it, but I don't I don't really see how.
Like, what wave action just because there's no there's no fetch because it's in there. It's kind of facing
the opposite way. It's almost like 90 degrees to the main
lake body
looking at the picture.
Oh yeah. Yeah, yeah.
Now that's helpful.
>> Gary,
were you planning to have
the sand higher than the level of the 4x4s
or were the 4x4s
going to be higher than the level of the sand?
>> The 4x4s
are going to be higher than the level of the sand.
So that'll give you a little more protection.
Yeah. So
And
>> we do not yeah, we don't get big waves in the in the cove. It just doesn't have any any room to develop.
>> One of the one of the ideas that I had from the the preceding plan,
and you talk about the size of the sandbox,
it
looked like from your drawing, was 25 feet
wide along the lakeside,
15 feet deep into the yard, then 15 feet across the back, so it was like a trapezoid.
Yeah.
>> On the plan
where we had the high rock wall, you know, one of my thoughts was if we made it a 15 by 15 square,
that gave some more of the rock wall to protect around the edge
so that that
prevented the sand from going right around the corner and into the lake.
You've eliminated that concern a little bit with the four by four posts
going in.
When I did, you know, my
back of the envelope calculation
on
the 15 feet by 15 feet, which is three yards by three yards,
which is about,
you know, nine yards,
and you put 10 yards of sand in there,
you know,
that's a lot of sand that
raises
that up.
No, was five
yards by five yards is 25.
But I came up, you know, it was going to be at least a foot of sand
high.
And so I guess, you know, you're saying you got 15
total. It would be important to know
how much sand you're going to move up by the house for whatever future
need you have.
But you need to know how deep to dig the hole before you start putting the sand in there, or else you're going to get a
bunch of sand in there and then you're going to find
that it's,
I guess you just add more four by fours to it. But it would be nice to have that kind of detail
on
how deep you expected the sand to be, how many four by fours it took to get up so we can see how much
extra height there is on the four by four perimeter
around
the sand, and that would give us the opportunity to make a good judgment on
do we want to put a swale in
on the landward side of all the
three sides of the sandbox
as
was described in the New Hampshire document.
And that's the kind of detail that I didn't see here.
>> Yeah, and I mean, I couldn't do the math if you had a gun to my head on how much sand that would take. I couldn't either if you had a gun to my head, but if I was sitting here in the other side, I understand. I like the idea
of,
you
know,
I was just going, you know, 25 feet because that was the size of wall. I'm good with let's move that into,
know, like 17 or something like that. So we have what's eight, four feet
on either side.
Yep. Right.
And
then
quite honestly,
I mean,
I was thinking I was gonna have sand left over that we would just pull back up.
If
and that would,
know,
how much sand it would take to do that.
I don't know what we'd have to go
take that as a homework assignment and go look into that.
But I think there's probably enough there to,
know,
get my intent is to have just a play area for the kids to know,
know, a kind of place to hang out. And I like that thought.
And it's smaller than what,
you know, that's why, you know, we're having this discussion. It's a work in progress. So that's this is good.
>> Have you actually talked to a contractor or a landscaper that would be able to get in there before mid
March?
>> So
I've talked to a guy who's done landscaping
for me at my previous house.
And he did the work over on
for Todd
over on
next door on one.
But
I'm going to be putting this out to bid.
And
but I have not talked to another guy
about this. When this plan comes together,
then I'll, you
know, do that.
The guy that I'm working with now,
amount of money that it's going to cost requires me to do my due diligence on that
side of it and get another
bit.
Understand. Yep.
>> So so can we can we get this project done before
the lake
fills back up?
We certainly can get the sand out of there.
And if we if we don't have it,
you know,
we can get the stone wall properly built, but the
beach part
may have to wait
and we'd have to pull the sand up 200 feet. I don't know.
I mean, there's a there's a bunch of,
you know, lot of unknowns on that right now.
And I don't want to be wishy washy and
commit to something that I I, you know.
>> Nope, I understand.
The reason I mentioned that is because,
you know, normally,
we
got ourselves into this a little bit backwards,
but normally guys,
you know, one, the landscaper makes the plan for him and he comes in with a commitment, I will do it next winter, but we're talking about plans,
you know, in the July, August timeframe. So
that
you can get that commitment from the landscaper to come in and do that.
With it being, you know, mid February already, I think you might be hard pressed to get a guy to do your rock wall this season. Well,
>> yeah, I mean,
I was, I went up to Andover landscaping and then tried to get somebody to help me up there and nope I never I went there twice and
everybody's busy and then in COVID and then then this and then every time you turn around it's
you know
reason you know stuff's happening all over the world right so
slowing everything down. But yeah, that that the timeline is going to be
is
going to be tough.
Now I know Alma gave it was a two year
window
saying you know
this is approved for a two year window.
I don't know is that a that a same thing that you guys would do that I could get the work done within two years or
and I want to get it done as soon as possible but if if we got to wait for the next cycle with the water,
>> I mean, that's what we have to do. Well, in just trying to figure out a way ahead, one of the options is
that we make,
you know, instead of trying to design this during the commission meeting,
you know, we've given you a lot of good feedback now.
Maybe
we work on
getting the sand out of the lake,
you know, and I'm worried about
doing that because
the first thing that's going to happen is
it'll get soft enough for you to be able to get your shovel in the sand,
but the lake bed's going to be so soft at that point that moving a wheelbarrow through there is gonna be And next to
so
I'm
really concerned about just getting the sand out of the lake this year, and it would give you a long time to,
I
think we're getting close
on
having
an acceptable
solution.
I just don't know how many hours we can devote to coming up to that tonight.
And
>> when I don't think you'd be able to, yeah, I'm not confident that you'd be able to get
a landscape guy to come in and do
it once
we approved it. And so maybe
you just say,
and maybe we've got some latitude, I don't know, to have a stockpile
someplace without dragging all the sand the 200 feet away. Know, maybe
there's a way to cover up a pile of sand so that it doesn't wash into the lake.
While
we're, you know, trying to figure out the way ahead. I want to work with you. I just Yeah.
>> No,
no, that's
good. I mean,
thinking out loud, you know, if I put down a tarp or something where we want to put the new
beach,
anticipating
that we'll get there at some point, but then I have to move it again anyway, was on a tarp. I don't know. You'd
>> have to move it a little further back, but there's a difference between
25 feet away from the shoreline and 200 feet when you're trying to hauling.
>> Especially with that hill you have. Yeah.
Well, that's right. I bought
a little little
wheelbarrow hookup
to the
to the lawn tractor.
I you probably could put a yard in that and
anyways,
but yeah, so I've been thinking about all that too.
Believe me, I'm on the same page as you guys.
I think this was good discussion.
Timeframe,
sand is priority,
design
we're pretty close.
Joe's been great to work with on this stuff.
We get feedback, this feedback will prove invaluable.
We can
I don't want to speak for you, Joe, but,
you know, I think we've got enough here now to,
make some adjustments? I'm not quite sure exactly what they are. I have to look through the notes here.
And then I don't know.
Get get
another
meeting,
get on the agenda again. Again, I I wanna respect your time. Here we're going almost an hour in on on my time. I know you got other business, so I I I don't want to
hold you guys up.
>> Right,
I agree with
Commissioner Morrison that we really can't spend much more time trying
to design this thing on the fly.
I think you've heard our concerns
then
about
making sure that you have effective
erosion of sand from the proposed perch beach
into the like,
involve
a reduction in, a small reduction in size,
little bit of setback
in
that,
and
the
and the,
or
retainable.
And
again,
I think to the point that having
a contractor
who can
speak to the
details
of how the work will be conducted,
what measures
will be taken,
in construction,
to prevent erosion, all that sort of thing
is something we'll have to
address at an interim meeting.
Yeah. Can certainly take it upon our agenda
for our March meeting.
And again,
I believe this
give you time to get the work done this season,
but as
Commissioner Lawson pointed out, it's pretty unlikely you're going to find a contractor
who would be available
on that short notice. Right.
I think that the one thing that
we might, if I'll have to get back and review,
details
of
our regulations,
certainly,
if approved,
any part of
it would be the
removal
of the dock,
which is, you know, pretty much just a whole separate thing.
And that's something which, as you say, is going to be hand tools and a
fairly narrow window
of being able to,
a, dig in the lick bed but not sink in.
So,
I think we'll have to leave this
application for the time being. As
I say, we'll bring it up again
at our next meeting, and
we'll try to keep some communication open
between
you, Gary, and Joe and Commissioner
it develops,
and particularly
try and come up with a
plan that we have
time to adequately review
prior to our next consideration.
Commissioner
>> Larson, yes. I do have one other question,
I guess, about the remediation,
and that is,
is it worth it?
And I think it is
to put some kind of erosion
perimeter
around the sand piles that are on the lake bed right now so that as the spring rains come in,
it doesn't, you know, continue to wash the sand
into the lake prior to us being able to get the sand
out of the lake.
You know, and that I don't think is hard to do. You just put some hay bales around the area there.
But right now, you know, all the water that runs down that slope
from his yard over there where the beach currently is, is just washing more sand into the lake.
>> Yeah.
Yeah,
I don't see that as a problem.
I guess I just have to find some hay bales.
I don't know if I find it, but I'll find it. Or the
>> you could do the filter fabric,
the black fabric walls.
Yeah. They stake around
construction Silt
>> fence or hinge. Silt fence, yeah, silt fence, thank you.
>> You can get that ready made at Home Depot or
any other
home improvement
store,
so that would be readily available. It might even be easier to work with than the hay bales, trying to slap those around.
But I think Commissioner Larson does have a good point there
that
we're at a season when
erosion is likely to happen and trying to and taking
measures to prevent that,
now and even while you're trying to move the sand, you know, you're disturbing it, and that's likely to cause erosion. So, silt vents or hay bales
to
>> prevent movement into the lake bed. So, it's a fill fence, F I L L fence?
S I L T.
Oh.
>> Filt fence, so yeah,
tilt,
tilt, got it. Okay.
I was hearing F Okay, so it's okay
all right.
One, just one other suggestion.
I don't know if it's inside a protocol or not, but as we put together
the next
iteration here,
Could we have a working session with one of the commissioners
to get some
feedback
perhaps
and then
and then that way we maybe can
short circuit some of the
lengthy Any discussion during the
>> discussion. We have to have our discussions have to occur in open meeting,
in public meetings.
Okay. Again, you can you can we can have some informal
communication,
certainly keeping us posted
and as I say timely notification
so we don't have to try to do this on the fly. Okay. Yeah, I want to I want to eliminate that. Yeah.
>> Okay. All right, so we'll
throw a draft out or have some communication.
>> Gary,
would like to get in the record. We have your permission to exceed our sixty five day time requirement to act on the application.
We are allowed up to sixty five days at your permission to
extend that window.
>> Okay.
So yeah, I'm not.
Yes,
I guess you have my permission.
Thank you. Thank you.
>> Thanks for remembering that, Joe, because I had that in my notes too.
A sixty five day extension will put us at April 15
from the current deadline.
Okay,
well, folks, I'd like to move on now
to our other,
agenda item,
our other application,
which is
2,129
for
the project proposed
retail at
5 8th Road.
Hold on here a second while I pull up that.
And
who do we have on the call representing the applicants here?
And you are?
>> Hi, Mr. Chairman. My name is Matthew Bruton. I'm an engineer from BL Companies
here on behalf of the applicant. Okay.
>> Okay.
My notes,
say that we have had,
one minor update.
We received a revised plan
that included
a sidewalk along Lake Road.
As far as I'm aware, there have been no other material
changes in the plan,
and certainly nothing would be germane to our consideration.
Is that correct?
>> That's correct, Mr. Chairman. I'm happy to share a plan on the screen if you want. I can
show you that sidewalk if that would please the Commission.
>> Anybody else have need to see that? I'll I'll look at it.
Commissioner Larson,
>> Commissioner Monroe, anybody want to, pull that up, or can we just? I saw it, man. How did you how did you figure out where to put the sidewalk?
>> Mr. Larson, the sidewalk was a request
or a future request that we're expecting to receive from the Planning and Zoning Commission
as it would need to be in the public right of way. We placed it between
the existing curb line of Lake Road and the property line
for this parcel. So it's a long a long Lake Road in between those two boundaries of the curb line of the property line. Did you had any discussion with Jim Halsey on
that?
>> I spoke to him briefly about it
after
the first meeting.
I have not spoken to him since about it since it's being placed. We obviously have not gone to the Planning and Zoning Commission yet. Yep.
>> Okay, because
I am the chairman of the planning and zoning commission.
I don't know where the town was wanting the sidewalk to go, but I know Jim had,
asked Jim, do you know where the sidewalk's going to go? And he said, yep.
>> When I spoke to him, I think you're pretty close.
Where is being placed? Yeah. Again, happy to once we get to planning and zoning, if you guys wanted to
shift a few feet in either direction, you know, not not a big deal on our part,
but took a took a stab at it based on our conversation, and, I think it's in a a good spot for for the moment. Okay. Yep. I do not need to see the drawing.
>> In any event, I'm not sure that it's germane to our consideration from a wetland's point of view. I have a communication here from Agent Wagner.
>> You might have froze up on us, George. We didn't hear you.
>> Okay,
can you hear me now? I haven't clicked any controls.
Yep.
Okay,
again, as I say, I have some unstable
internet connection,
and of course, I don't know when I'm blanking out.
Somebody has to tell me.
Okay,
the communication I have here relates
to the stormwater management. But again,
this application
relates
to
wetlands and water courses, and specifically to the fact that this
parcel
is
withinat
least a portion of the parcelis within 200 feet of
the Cheney Brook
Watercourse and the associated wetlands.
So, I'm not sure that the,
you know, stormwater management from the property, which actually runs down
to Court Route 6,
would be germane to our discussion,
which would have to do with any potential impacts
on
Chaney Brook,
which is, of course, on the other side of Lake Road.
As
far as I can tell, and according to the application,
there's
no anticipated
impact
of this project
on that watercourse
or wetlands,
largely due to the fact that Lake Road
is at an elevation higher
than the
project and the parcel,
and
effectively acts as a berm
between the project area
and the
wetlands and water course.
So,
unless I'm mistaken,
we could
act on this application
without further consideration,
since the application again relates specifically
to the brook
and the, you know, the 200 foot upland,
so called upland review area.
Perhaps we should say contiguous area rather than upland in this case.
So,
to Commissioner Larson,
did you have any comment
on the application or questions or comments?
>> Only that Matt seemed to be raised his hand, so he must have something.
>> Thanks, Mr. Larson. I was just was just gonna say, Mr. Chairman, I don't, I don't disagree with anything that you've said.
This site is downhill,
and away from Lake Road and Cheney Brook and everything flows towards Route 6 as you said. So I was just gonna reiterate what you said that we have no direct or indirect
impacts on the wetlands.
Everything is just in the Upland Review area.
>> So I'd like to make a motion that we approve permit application
21Dash29
Gerrit Homes LLC 580 Lake Road
construction of a 10,640
square foot single story
retail building with utilities and paid parking and loading area.
All right.
We have a second for Commissioner Monroe.
Yep. Okay.
>> And I would, again, note that as a
condition that
our finding
that there will be
negative or no impact
on the wetland or watercourse
under consideration.
That finding is part of our decision
or supports our decision.
Okay, so with that, any further discussion?
Seeing none, I'll
call for a vote, and then we'll do it by roll call. Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Munro?
And aye, Chairman Elliott, also vote aye, so the motion carries three-zero-zero.
You got your wetlands permit.
Now you get to go to the other guys
and see what they have to say.
>> I appreciate your time tonight, gentlemen. Thank you so much. Appreciate it. And thanks, Joe, for your help. Alright.
>> You're excused from the call.
And we can move on to our agenda.
Okay, I guess the rest of it is up to Adrian Wagner, the other business,
enforcement actions, agent report, so forth. So take it away.
>> Yeah, the only thing I
got that I wanted to share was I received an application from
from DEP
for permit application for use of pesticides and state waters.
It's for Andover Lake.
I was applied for on behalf of Alma and
they're required the
company that's performing the work
is required to
notify
the local inland wetlands agency.
So I just wanted to share that with you guys.
>> We don't have can give you a little background on that if you'd like. Yeah, take it as a herbicide
application of some. Yeah, yeah. So we had been talking with, I think it's Northeast Aquatic Services
about ways to mitigate the weeds in the lake because of the issues that we had last year with the Elodea.
And they had proposed several different options,
a couple of which we want to be prepared to pursue if we need to.
One of them is the use of the herbicides in the lake. And they've
done a pretty good job
in terms of selecting the
herbicides that they would use. We were very clear that we didn't want to kill any of the fish or have any other problems.
And this is something that they've done on a regular basis.
The permitting process
generally takes about six months with DEEP.
So we have to ask them to
start the process as soon as possible so that if
we find by the end of July that we're having a weed problem, we can elect to bring them in and do something to try and mitigate it.
There will be another permit coming through for
doing some potential dredging
for the weeds as well. That's another method that they have where they do what they call preferential dredging, where they'll go into a weed bed and they'll dredge it out and pull the weeds out.
That's something they might do for lily pads or it might do for
cattails, that sort of thing.
But that I believe is
something that is in your hands. It's not DEEP.
They indicated that that wasn't a DEEP permit, that would be a wetlands permit.
So that's yet to come. But this one is,
just getting it started in case we need it this summer.
>> Okay.
So it was basically an FYI.
We don't have any jurisdiction over that
activity,
so.
Okay.
And of course, the ongoing
conservative
nutrients
entering the lake, which are, of course, I'm sure supporting that healthy population of Elodea.
>> Yes.
And that's our biggest problem is how do we get our hands around that and clear up any
septic system problems around the lake that are causing additional issues? Not
to mention fertilizers on lawns.
Oh yeah.
Yes, that's the
worst.
>> Again, unfortunately, we don't have any role to play in that,
>> so all we can do is wish you best of luck. And all we can do is educate. That's about our only choice and beg.
>> Cherry, I have a comment,
since we have an Alma member here.
With the with this
herbicide and
pesticides that they're talking about
using to kill some of these weeds.
Isn't going to work unless we don't keep bringing the stuff into the lake after the
herbicides been put in there. I mean, if you, if it takes a year or two years or three years to get rid of those weeds, but we keep doing the same thing that we're doing, which is
taking our canoes and our kayaks to a lake in New York somewhere that has all this stuff growing
out of control
and flopping our canoe
back into the lake. It's just gonna start instantly all over again.
>> Yeah, that's another
area that we spend a lot of time actually trying to figure out how we can do it. I mean, we do educate the members on that. We try and make it clear that they, you know, so they all know not to do that and to wash your boat if you take it anywhere else.
We actually had
a guy that came to the lake last year, he wanted to rent boats to people and we turned them down for that very reason because we weren't comfortable that we could be sure that he wasn't bringing weeds in.
So yeah, we know that that's an uphill battle for us. That's something that we do spend some time and energy on trying to figure out, can we put a wash station at
the right of way so that they would actually,
people bringing their boats in would automatically wash them, we wouldn't have to worry about it.
It becomes difficult because then you have to deal with vandalism and things like that. And you don't want to put bleach out and where kids are going to come and hurt themselves with it.
So, but yeah, we know that that's a big problem. And it's a question I ask people every time I see them on the lake, if they don't have a sticker on their boat, I ask them, are they a member? Did they wash their boat?
You know, they almost always say yes. So they know, or they know to say yes, I don't know which.
>> Right.
I
know it seems like a lot of the things that we do around
the lake, a lot of people just don't understand what what's going on, and and that's the reason why they make bad decisions. Yeah, we can more
information out there somehow make it more
like, you know, we're all gonna do this together because it's not, you know, it's a good idea.
Mean, I took the time today to look through some of the chemicals that
you're gonna be using. And,
I know they say they are safe,
but do not forget, somebody used to say that smoking cigarettes was safe too
for about thirty years before they finally said, Oh, really, it is not safe.
>> This is all pretty hypothetical at the moment, I'm afraid we digress
a little bit from the
Commission's business.
You can
take that up as a sidebar conversation,
okay? Okay, all All
right. Then, in any of this, you see, it's right
now we're just dealing with an FYI,
and it remains to be seen whether any action will be required.
>> Okay, well, exciting as this is, I'm going to sign off then. Okay, you don't need me anymore. We'll let you go. Have a good night, guys. Hey, Jeff. Bye.
Okay, so have there been any enforcement actions or?
>> Not quite a month.
Hard to see anything under all the snow.
So I haven't, I haven't heard of anything yet.
No,
no upland approvals.
There's one
that I just I just received a permit for all. I'll have to brief you for it on
about on the next meeting. I just received the application at the end of last week,
so I'll put that on the next month's agenda.
>> Okay,
good enough.
So,
it sounds like we're winding down the regular business.
We have a
meeting scheduled for Monday, March 7.
Actually, I'll remind you,
we've warned that we will have a hearing
for
receive
public comment
on our
proposed revisions
to our regulations,
and
our meeting will actually directly
follow
that
hearing,
and
presumably approval of the regulations
will be an item on the agenda for that meeting,
as well as of course continuing with 2127,
which we hope will be in good order and received in advance,
well in advance
of the meeting, so we have time to review it.
Any last minute thoughts or comments?
If not, I will happily
ask for
unanimous consent
to adjourn the meeting
at what is it now? We'll call it 08:30PM.
Any objection?
Seeing none,
we can stand adjourned.
Thanks,
Abby, for being here, and I hope that you will continue to be able to be with us. I got your mail and realize
that you're in a
hard spot,
and
will
be flexible
so that you can be flexible.
>> Thank you very much. I don't anticipate it will affect my
abilities here, don't worry, but I just wanted to let you know, so thank you. Right.
>> Okay,
so once again, stand adjourned,
and we can all press the little red leave button.
Good night, everybody. All right. Good night.